A Guide to The Virginia League for Planned Parenthood Archives, 1935-2004
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
The Virginia League for Planned Parenthood Archives, 1935-2004
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M333
2.49 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Grace S. Sparks, Executive Director of the Virginia League for Planned Parenthood, donated the collection on July 26, 2004.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Virginia League for Planned Parenthood, Inc. received its charter from the State Corporation Commission in 1940, two years before the national organization changed its name from the Birth Control Federation of America to the Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc. The founders of the Virginia League for Planned Parenthood include Ellen Harvie Smith, President of the Virginia Tuberculosis Association; Mrs. Fred Alexander, Chairman of Health and Welfare for the Virginia Federation of Women's Clubs; Douglas Southall Freeman, historian and editor of the Richmond News-Leader; Coleman Baskerville, architect; and Dr. H. Hudnall Ware, Head of the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology at the Medical College of America. The organization dedicated its early efforts to education and advocacy for family planning and women's health. In 1975, the Virginia League for Planned Parenthood opened a clinic that offered health services to women and adolescents using a sliding fee scale. Since 1994, the clinic has offered first- trimester abortions. Reproductive health care and education for men and women of all ages continues to be a central focus of the Virginia League for Planned Parenthood.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of publications, histories, newspaper clippings, letters to the editor, Richmond City proclamations, photographs, scrapbooks, and ephemera. The materials range in date from 1935-2004. The scrapbooks contain newspaper clippings and publications.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by format: papers; photographs; items from photo albums; city proclamations and miscellaneous; scrapbooks; and ephemera. The papers, photographs, city proclamations, and ephemera are organized alphabetically and chronologically therein. The items from photo albums were removed from their original photo albums for the purpose of preservation. The items are grouped by photo album and are numbered to reflect their original order. The scrapbooks are arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Documents and Publications 1940-2004 (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
  Contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, publications, and historical essays on the organization.
  alphabetical
  - Sparks, Grace S., Director 1989-2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Histories, 1950s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Histories, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters to the editor, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters to the editor, 1995-2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters to the editor, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1989-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1995-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Planned Parenthood Action Network, c. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Planned Parenthood Federation of America publications, 1945, 1962, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Publications, 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Publications, 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Publications, 1980s-2004 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Photographs, 1980s-2004, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-11)
  Contains miscellaneous photographs.
  - Cheek, Mary Tyler, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Every Child a Wanted Child party, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - March for Women's Lives, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - March for Women's Lives, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous negatives, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Office photographs, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Planned Parenthood Office, 1218 West Franklin St., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Praxis, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Photo albums, 1985-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1-17)
  Contains photographs, articles, and flyers that were removed from photo albums for preservation.
  Items are arranged and numbered in the same order as they were found in the photo albums.
  - "45 Years in the Family Business", 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1-9)
  - Photo album, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10-13)
  - Special Friends photo album, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 14-17)
- City of Richmond Proclamations, Certificates of Recognition, Guest Book, 1980-2000 (Box 3-4)
  Contains City of Richmond Proclamations, certificates of recognition, and a guest book.
  - Family Sexuality Education Month, Certificate of Recognition, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Campaign to Save Our Children, City of Richmond Proclamation, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Guest book with photographs, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Let's Listen-Let's Talk Month, City of Richmond Proclamation, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Let's Listen-Let's Talk Month, City of Richmond Proclamation, c. 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Let's Listen-Let's Talk Month, City of Richmond Proclamation, c. 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Margaret Sanger Day, Certificate of Recognition and City of Richmond Proclamation, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Teen Preganancy Prevention Month, City of Richmond Proclamation, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Scrapbooks 1935-1969 (Box 5-7)
  - Scrapbook, 1942-1943 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1935, 1944-1954 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1944-1961 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1959-1966 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook, 1966-1969 (Box 7)
- Ephemera, c. 2000-2004 (Map-case 74)
  Contains signs, posters, and miscellaneous ephemera.
  - Behind Every Choice is a Story. Roe v. Wade 1973-2003 poster, 2003
  - March for Women's Lives poster, 2004
  - March for Women's Lives tube, 2004
  - Stand Up for Choice! sign, 2004